译：凡心春水
美国华纳兄弟影片公司出品
(TYPEWRITER KEYS CLACKING)
当时正是一八九一年
WATSON: The year was 1891.
欧洲的局势阴云密布
Storm clouds were brewing over Europe.
法德两国成剑拔弩张之势
France and Germany were at each other's throats...
都由那一系列的爆炸案引起
...the result of a series of bombings
有人说是民族主义者的作为
Some said it was Nationalists...
也有说是无政府主义者
others, the anarchists
But as usual...
当然 我的朋友 夏洛克-福尔摩斯
...my friend Sherlock Holmes...
他的理论依旧与众不同
...had a different theory entirely.
斯特拉斯堡发生爆炸 号外号外
MAN 1: Bombing in Strasbourg! Read all about it!
谢谢
MAN 2: Thank you. MAN 1: Anarchists suspected...
（《每日图报》 斯特拉斯堡爆炸）
无政府主义者涉嫌斯特拉斯堡爆炸案
...in Strasbourg bombing!
Bombing in Strasbourg!
(CHATTERING INDISTINCTLY)
(BELL TOLLING)
(MAN WHISTLES)
你什么时候开始当邮递员了
When did you start working for the postal service?
那个人是你啊
That was you back there.
破案破到这个地步还真倒楣
Shame your activities have landed you in the gutter.
包裹很可疑 敢问收件人是哪位
A curious parcel. Who's the intended recipient?
Why don't we discuss that over dinner tonight?
不如等晚上吃饭时候再聊吧
午饭我有空
- I'm free for lunch.
- Hmm. I'm not.
可我没空
萨沃伊餐厅怎么样 晚上八点
How about the Savoy, 8:00?
正合我意
- Splendid.
- Hmm.
And will you be coming as yourself?
到时候你会现出原形吗
很有可能
Most likely.
有三个人跟踪了我们半英哩路 他们动机
Three men have been following
you for the last half mile...
...their motives highly unsavory.
相当不单纯
不好
No.
(GASPS)
对了 他们不是在追我 而是在护送我
Oh, and, by the way, they're not pursuing
me, they're escorting me.
And instead of three, there seems to be, uh, four.
而且好像不止三个人 应该有四个
Heh.
要小心轻放 艾琳
Steady hands with that, Irene.
Oh, I don't think it's my hands
you have to worry about.
现在需要小心的人应该不是我
别在脸上下重手 我们晚上还有约会
Be careful with the face, boys. We
do have a dinner date tonight.
餐前面包少吃点
Don't fill up on bread.
(WHISTLING MOZART'S "EINE KLEINE NACHTMUSIK")
(WHISTLING CONTINUES)
后面我忘记了
I forgot the rest.
现在想起来了
Oh, it's coming back now.
(GRUNTING)
THUG: Aah!
Aah!
有条子
Peelers!
(THUG WHISTLING)
(WHISTLING CONTINUES)
(GRUNTING)
(BULLETS CLATTERING)
现在开拍三十四号藏品
AUCTIONEER: We now come to Lot 34...
一尊雕饰异常华丽的埃及石棺
...Egyptian sarcophagus of outstanding provenance...
...retrieved from the Valley of the Kings.
发掘自国王峡谷
你的报酬 大夫 他说非常感谢
Your payment, doctor. He sends his thanks.
谁愿意出价
Who will bid 100 pounds?
一百英镑
One hundred. Thank you, sir.
请转交给他 他等着要的
HOFFMANSTAHL: Please, give
this to him. He's expecting it.
Tell him our friend thinks I delivered it to his sister.
就说那位朋友以为我把信给他姐姐了
Uh... Stay...
请坐
...while I check the contents.
等我看一下东西
他说全部报酬都在这儿
I was assured full payment would be there.
Yes, but assured by whom?
是吧
但他又是谁呢
Have you ever met him in person?
你有没有见过他本人
Or like me, have you been...?
还是像我一样
别动 别动 千万别动
Hold it, hold it. Please, don't move it.
根据尺寸和重量来看
Judging from size and weight, it's not
the payment you were expecting.
这可不是你想要的报酬
依我看这东西应该会相当劲爆
I'd wager the contents are rather more incendiary.
- Who is this?
- It's...
他是谁
他是
你好 亲爱的
Hello, darling.
(WHIRRING)
Oh, dear. I told you not to move it. It seems
a secondary charge has been activated.
哦 天哪 告诉过你不要动的
看来备用引爆器被激活了
美女 我处理包裹的时候可能要你协助
Sweet thing, I might need your help
in the disposal of this parcel.
One thousand six hundred, 1700, 1800.
一千六百英镑
一千七百英镑
一千八百英镑
祝你好运
- Well, good luck. HOLMES: One million pounds.
一千九百英镑
一百万英镑
(CROWD GASPS)
Oh, and by the way, fire.
哦 还有 着火了
Fire!
(CROWD CLAMORS)
Leave my side, you'll be dead in an hour.
你要是逃走 一小时内必死无疑
记得晚饭不要迟到
And don't be late for dinner.
出了这种状况
My schedule will be quite tight because
of these activities here.
我接下来的行程会排得很满的
- I've never been late in my life, only early.
- Fashionably.
我这辈子从不迟到 只会提前
很有品味
Mm. Mm-mm. Mm!
非常狡猾 就算逃跑也那么自信
Very witty. So confident, even in retreat.
I'll hold onto that. We'll read
it together over an aperitif.
这个我来保管
等喝开胃酒的时候再一起看吧
好啊 边吃边看好戏
Fine. Dinner and a show.
等着 相信我 我是靠这个吃饭的
Stay. Trust me. This is what I do for a living.
赫尔-霍芬斯塔 你真的很走运
Herr Hoffmanstahl, you should count yourself lucky.
你替他办事的这神秘人物不是普通罪犯
This faceless man with whom you find yourself
in business is no ordinary criminal.
他是个犯罪之王
He's the Napoleon of crime. Fortunately,
you now have me as an ally.
幸运的是 你现在有我这个盟友
我是个小有名气的私家侦探
I'm a consulting detective of some repute.
Perhaps you've heard of me? My name is Sherlock...
也许你听说过我 我的名字叫福尔
(MUFFLED EXPLOSION)
(COUGHS)
...Holmes.
摩斯
MAN: Hyah!
(HORSES WHINNYING)
(CHATTERING)
A fresh pot of tea. Thank you, George.
帮我换一杯茶 谢谢 乔治
好的 艾德勒小姐
GEORGE: Yes, Miss Adler.
MAN: Fine choice, this place.
选得不错 这个地方
Do you have the letter?
信带来了吗
It was taken.
它被拿走了
拿走了 那真是太不幸了
MAN: Taken? Now, that is unfortunate.
During the chaos created by your package.
都是你包裹惹出来的麻烦
Thank you.
谢谢
Perhaps if you had shared your plans.
也许你该早点告诉我你的计划
You wish to know my plans now, do you?
你想要知道我的计划 对吗
Did you imagine, Miss Adler, that
something would happen to you?
你在怀疑我会对你不利 艾德勒小姐
Is that why you chose to meet here in a public place?
所以才会把见面地点选在公共场合
Your favorite restaurant?
你最喜欢的餐厅
(CLINKING)
(DOOR CLOSES)
I don't blame you.
这不怪你
都怪我自己
I blame myself.
It's been apparent to me for some time that
you had succumbed to your feelings for him.
我早就发现你没办法
控制住对他的感情
And this isn't the first occasion Mr. Holmes
has inconvenienced me in recent months.
这也不是福尔摩斯
第一次给我带来不便了
The question is...
问题在于
...what to do about it.
应该如何去应对
But that's my problem to solve now.
但是
现在这是我自己的问题
I no longer require your services.
我不再需要你的协助了
(UTENSILS CLINKING SOFTLY)
(DISHES CRASHING)
(ADLER GRUNTS)
(CHATTERING)
(WOMAN CHUCKLES)
福尔摩斯：诡影游戏
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
(KNOCKS ON DOOR)
哈德森夫人
Mrs. Hudson?
哈德森夫人在吗
Oh, Mrs. Hudson?
(GLADSTONE BARKS)
福尔摩斯 在家吗
Holmes, you in there?
(SIGHS)
Your hedge needs trimming.
你家篱笆该修剪了
(GOAT BLEATS)
HOLMES (WHISPERINGS) Where am I?
你猜我在哪儿
我不管你在哪儿 准备好出门就行
WATSON: I don't care where you
are as long as you're ready.
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
我在等你
HOLMES: I'm waiting.
(ANIMAL HOOTS)
I'm not gonna play this game.
我不想玩捉迷藏
Remember, I have to catch the last...
记得吗 我得赶上末班
(BLEATS)
车
- ...train. HOLMES (IN NORMAL VOICE): Uh-oh.
很不幸你死了
- That's you dead, I'm afraid.
- You win.
你赢了
我输了 游戏结束
I lose. Game over.
HOLMES: Still don't see me?
还没找到我吗
(HOLMES LAUGHS)
真是意外啊
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
I'm not going out with you dressed like that.
穿成这样 我是不会和你出去的
Would you prefer I joined you in the fashion faux pas...
要不我和你一样穿上老掉牙的军外套
围上一条恶心的手工围巾怎么样
...of wearing fine military dress with
that heinous handmade scarf...
显然是你未婚妻的早期作品吧
...clearly one of your fiancée's early efforts?
Oh, how I've missed you, Holmes.
我想死你了 福尔摩斯
Have you? Why?
是吗
为什么
我几乎没有注意到你走了
I've barely noticed your absence. Then
again, I'm knee-deep in research.
我一直专注于研究
从羊的肾上腺中提取液体
Extracting fluids from the adrenal glands of sheep...
...and designing my own urban camouflage...
设计我专用的都市迷彩服
...all the while verging on a decisive breakthrough...
同时步步逼近 我整个侦探生涯中
...in the single most important case
of my career, perhaps of all time.
最重要的案子的决定性突破点
也许将永载史册
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACH)
Mrs. Hudson, how are you?
哈德森夫人 你好啊
Oh. I'm so pleased to see you, doctor.
Thank you for inviting me tomorrow.
见到你很高兴 大夫
谢谢你的邀请
And thank you for looking after Gladstone.
我也很感谢你对爱犬的照料
Dear, dear sickly-sweet Nanny, might I have a word?
亲爱的热情过度的管家夫人 能说句话吗
美味
Yummy. Feed the snake, woman.
你去喂蛇吧
You feed it.
你去喂吧
Touchy, touchy.
妇人之仁
大夫 你必须送他去疗养院
Doctor, you must get him to a sanatorium.
He's been on a diet of coffee, tobacco, and coca leaves.
他最近不是咖啡 烟草 就是可可汁
He never sleeps. I hear multiple voices
as if he's rehearsing a play.
他不睡觉了
整天南腔北调的就像在排练话剧
(CHUCKLES)
Leave him to me.
我会处理的
你是不是该给山羊吃打虫药了
Don't you have a goat that needs worming?
Oh, how kind of you to remind me.
谢谢你提醒我
So much to look forward to. What
would I do without you?
我都快等不及了
没了你我该怎么办
Good luck with your patient, doctor.
祝你的病人顺利康复 大夫
Why are you here?
你来干什么
I'm getting married tomorrow.
我明天就结婚了
Oh! Embrace me.
拥抱一下
华生要结婚了
Watson's getting married.
你掉了几斤肉嘛 福尔摩斯
- You've lost a few pounds, Holmes.
- Yes, and you've picked them up.
是啊 都到你身上去了
- Noshing on Mary's muffins, no doubt.
- Ha.
肯定没少吃玛丽的松饼
Pour us a brandy. The stag party has begun.
倒两杯白兰地
单身派对现在开始
这是我们最后的冒险 华生
It is our last adventure, Watson.
I intend to make the most of it.
我一定不会浪费的
WATSON: I see you've made good use of my old office.
看来我以前的办公室也没浪费
喜欢我的蜘蛛网吗
HOLMES: Do you like my spider's web?
WATSON: Is that what you call it?
怎么叫这名字
Follow that strand.
你看那条线
Question: What do a scandal involving
an Indian cotton tycoon...
请问
（印度棉花大亨下台）
与印度棉花大亨有关的丑闻
（鸦片商人吸毒过量）
中国鸦片商人吸毒过量身亡
...the overdose of a Chinese opium trader...
...bombings in Strasbourg and Vienna...
斯特拉斯堡和维也纳爆炸案
（匹兹堡钢铁巨头死亡）
以及美国钢铁巨头之死
...and the death of a steel magnate
in America all have in common?
都有什么共同点
WATSON: Well, according to your diorama,
Professor James Moriarty.
根据你的立体模型来看
是詹姆斯-莫里亚蒂教授
HOLMES: Indeed.
一点没错
Mathematical genius. Celebrated author and lecturer.
数学天才 著名作家和演讲家
HOLMES: Boxing champion at Cambridge...
剑桥时代是拳击冠军
...where he made friends with
our current prime minister.
（奥地利王储自杀）
同时也与现任首相成了好朋友
你有什么证据来支持你的观点吗
Do you have any evidence to substantiate your claim?
(HOLMES CHUCKLES)
（炸弹危机化解 拍卖行逃过一劫）
这个
This. Now do you see?
（霍芬斯塔医生心脏病突发去世）
现在明白了吗
霍芬斯塔医生之死
WATSON: Dr. Hoffmanstahl's death?
- Yes.
没错 我听你提过他 盛赞他的医德
I've heard you speak of him, extolling his virtues.
霍芬斯塔是医学创新前沿的开拓者
Hoffmanstahl was at the forefront of
medical innovations, a true pioneer.
就在前不久
Just the other day, I averted an explosion
that was intended for him.
我化解了一起针对他的炸弹袭击
Says here he died of a heart attack.
这里说他死于心脏病
Has all my instruction been for naught? You
read the official statement and believe it.
我的谆谆教诲都白费了吗
你还在看官方报导而且居然会相信它
这是较量 老伙计 暗中的较量
It's a game, dear man, a shadowy game.
教授和我就像是猫和老鼠
We're playing cat and mouse, the professor
and I. Cloak and dagger.
斗篷和匕首
I thought it was spider and fly?
难道不是蜘蛛和苍蝇吗
（甲醛）
I'm not a fly, I'm a cat.
我才不是苍蝇 我是猫
Not a mouse, but a dagger.
不是老鼠 是匕首
You're drinking embalming fluid.
你喝的是尸体防腐液
Ooh. Yes. Care for a drop?
是的 来一杯吗
You do seem...
你是有点
兴奋      疯癫
- Excited?
- Manic.
我承认      几乎近于
- I am.
- Verging on...
神经质      神经病
- Ecstatic?
- Psychotic.
- Should've brought a sedative.
- I'll give my life to see his demise.
我真该给你带点镇定剂
我拼上性命也要扳倒他
He must be stopped before his evil
machinations come to a crescendo.
一定要在他的邪恶阴谋得逞之前阻止他
And how will he do all this?
他怎么实施阴谋呢
Don't be a dingy bird. Bad people
do bad things because they can.
别那么无知 坏人就是做得出坏事
No one, not the victims, the police,
the governments, not anyone...
无论受害者 警察还是政府 没有人
- Except the great Sherlock Holmes...
- Correct.
除了大侦探福尔摩斯      没错
以这种状态
- ...on this diet, will work it all out.
- Right.
才能破解迷局
没错
- Or thereabouts.
- Thereabouts, not quite there.
八九不离十
八九左右 还没到十
Here's to your good health.
祝你身体健康
Dingy bird.
无知的家伙
(GLADSTONE WHIMPERS THEN THUDS)
What have you done to Gladstone now?
你又对格莱斯顿做了什么
Ricinus communis. The fruit is highly toxic.
是蓖麻 它的果实有剧毒
He's barely breathing.
它快停止呼吸了
真个绝妙的时机
What an excellent opportunity.
这东西应该有效
This may be just the thing.
(GLADSTONE WHIMPERS)
你不介意我试验一下肾上腺提取物吧
Sorry, do you mind terribly if I try my adrenal extract?
我家的狗到底要死几次你才开心
How many times are you going to kill my dog, Holmes?
(GRUNTS THEN BARKS)
Took off like a monkey from a box.
跑得像出笼的猴子一样快
- Hmm.
- I may need one of those in a few hours.
说不定我等一下会用到这东西
HOLMES: Consider it a wedding gift.
就当作是结婚礼物吧
Watson, might we use an alternative exit?
华生 我们从另一个门出去吧
Is there something different about you?
你的样子有变过吗
I'm under observation.
我被人盯梢了
As you should be.
是该看住你
HOLMES: You drive.
你来开车
你打算整个晚上都带着胡子吗
WATSON: Will your beard be with us all night?
HOLMES: I'll remove it once we're
south of Trafalgar Square.
等过了特拉法加广场我就摘下来
WATSON: If you believe Moriarty
has you under observation...
如果莫里亚蒂的人在跟踪你的话
这样子是不是太显眼了
...isn't this a bit conspicuous?
高调到极致 就是隐蔽
HOLMES: It's so overt, it's covert.
特拉法加广场 你应该安全了
WATSON: Trafalgar Square. You must be safe by now.
好吧
(GRUNTS)
Why are you looking at me with such concern?
为什么你这么忧虑地看着我
I'm so very worried. Your vitality's
been drained from you.
因为我很担心你
你的生命力都快干涸了
婚姻是坟墓 我告诉你
- Marriage is the end, I tell you.
- I think of it as the beginning.
我认为是个新开始
世界末日
- Armageddon.
- Rebirth.
重获新生
- Restriction.
- Structure.
一种束缚
一个归宿
听女人的使唤
- Answering to a woman.
- Being in a relationship.
经营一段感情
A life in matrimony, the possibility of a family.
和谐美满的生活
还有共享天伦之乐
Who wants to die alone?
谁愿意孤独终老
We'll have a good old-fashioned romp tonight...
所以我们今天按照惯例彻夜狂欢
然后你去结婚生子 而我
...you'll settle down, have a family, and I'll die alone.
孤独终老
WATSON: Yes, that's about it.
差不多是这样
Perhaps it's better for one to die alone
than to live life in eternal purgatory.
我想孤独终老至少也胜过
一辈子活在人间地狱
Anyway...
随你便啦
Not bad, that.
灯还不错
So where are we going?
我们要去哪儿
MYCROFT: In the future, there'll be one of
those machines in every town in Europe.
未来这种机器会遍布欧洲的大街小巷
Loitering in the woodshed again, are we, Myccie?
又在柴房里游荡了 是吗 迈克
- Good evening, Sherly.
- Well.
晚上好 歇利
好
I see your bootmaker is ill, dear brother.
看来你的修鞋匠病了 亲爱的弟弟
As I detect that you've recently changed
the brand of soap with which you shave.
我发觉你换了一个牌子的肥皂来刮胡子
The chimney in the front room at Baker Street...
我想说你贝克街前厅的烟囱
...still needs a damn good sweeping up.
真的应该再好好打理一下才行
Were you aware that the hackney carriage by
which you arrived had a damaged wheel?
你是否发现来时坐的马车有个轮子坏了
Yes, the left. And it's plain to
the meanest intelligence...
当然 左轮
而且再笨的人也能猜到你最近给小提琴
...that you have recently acquired
a new bow for your violin.
买了把新琴弓
Same bow, new strings.
老琴弓 新琴弦
And may I deduce, Mycroft...?
Good evening, by the way.
如果我没猜错
迈克罗夫特 晚上好
免了
No.
他不握手
- He doesn't.
- May I deduce that you...
依我之见像你这样一个
...who rarely strays from the path that runs
from your home to the Diogenes Club...
不是在家就是在第欧根尼俱乐部
...and never on a Monday when they
serve your favorite potted shrimps...
而且从不错过每星期一小锅炒虾的人
来此必有比参加单身派对更重要的原因
...must be here for some far more important
reason than my stag party?
You know, he's nothing like as slow-witted as
you'd been leading me to believe, Sherly.
我觉得他根本就不是你说的
那种智力低下的笨蛋 歇利
你说得很对 华生大夫
No, you're quite right, Dr. Watson...
眼下的欧洲暗流涌动 局势随时都可能
...but with all the conflict in Europe at the
moment, the whole situation could...
请让一让
Excuse me.... suddenly erupt.
一触即发
I am here to avoid a dire catastrophe.
我来这里是要阻止一场大灾难
If the concerns of two nations...
某两个国家关系很紧张
...which shall remain nameless...
我不能透露它们的名字
...but I can tell you they speak French and German...
但它们分别说的是法语和德语
...are not dealt with tonight, I shall
be forced to go to Switzerland...
今晚若调解不好 我就不得不去瑞士
...to attend the ghastly peace summit in Reichenbach.
参加在莱辛巴赫举行的和平峰会
瑞士最讨厌的就是海拔太高
The worst thing about Switzerland is the altitude.
It gives me nosebleeds, exacerbates my asthma-1...
又让我流鼻血又加重我的哮喘
I'm so glad you invited your brother.
我很高兴你邀请了你哥哥
(BAND PLAYING LIVELY MUSIC)
(PEOPLE LAUGHING AND CHEERING)
This looks promising.
看起来很不错
WOMAN: And your poison of choice, gentlemen?
想要喝点什么 先生们
We'll start with the champagne. We
may need several more chairs.
先从香槟开始吧
我们可能还要几把椅子
Perhaps a good cigar.
给我来一支雪茄
And don't bother with the chairs.
还有
椅子就不必了
你哥哥究竟是干什么的
What is it your brother does exactly?
He's the keeper of the broom cupboard of state.
他是个给国家管管杂物的小干部
No ambition, no energy...
没野心 没激情 但我一直听人说
...yet I'm repeatedly told that he's indispensable
to the British government...
英国政府好像没了他不行
...particularly the Foreign Office.
尤其是外交部
- I would like to propose a toast.
- Really?
让我来敬你一杯
是吗
敬我的好友 医生 约翰
To my dear friend, Dr. John...
...um, Hamish Watson...
哈密什 华生
I'm right here.
我就在这儿
在这婚礼
...On the eve of his wedding. He...
的前夜
他
是我最好的伙伴
...has been the best companion.
不要再等等吗
Shouldn't we be waiting for the
boys from my rugby club?
我在橄榄球队的兄弟们呢
他一直帮助我们
He has always kept us... They couldn't attend.
他们来不了了
...flat-footed on the ground.
脚踏实地去生活
All of them? Hmm. The chaps from my medical school?
都没空吗 那我在医学院的那些同学呢
- They declined.
- The lads from the regiment?
我叫了 他们不来
那军队里的战友呢
没有人比他更加
- No man's better worth having at your side...
- Who is it you're looking for?
那你到底在找谁
值得你去结交
因为这里我一个认识的人都没有 对吗
Because I don't know a single damn person here, do I?
你这么激动干什么
There's no need for hysterics.
You know me and Mycroft.
你认识我 认识迈克罗夫特
- Don't be a ponce, Watson.
- Ponce?
别那么饥渴 华生
饥渴
You completely forgot about my stag party, didn't you?
你完全忘了我的单身派对 是不是
- Why are we here?
- Your very good health, doctor.
来这里做什么
祝你身体健康 大夫
很遗憾你的朋友们都没来
Shame none of your friends could make it.
(HOLMES & WATSON LAUGHING)
(LAUGHING)
I'm going to the gaming tables. I refuse
for this night to be a total loss.
我要过去玩上几把
我不能接受今晚就这么给毁了 把钱给我
- Give me my money.
- Happily. Give me the wedding ring.
很乐意
把结婚戒指给我
So now you're interested in being the best man.
现在怎么想起来自己是伴郎了
You're supposed to keep the ring anyway.
戒指确实应该由你保管没错
组织单身派对也应该是你的责任
Just as you're supposed to organize my stag party.
我是担心你把戒指赔进去 约翰
- Don't want to lose it on a bet.
- And invite my friends...
还有邀请我的朋友们 我有不少朋友
...of which, by the way, there are many.
You're the one with no friends...
没有朋友的人是你 孤僻怪人
...Sherly No Mates.
(CROWD CHEERING)
He's all "me, me, me," isn't he?
这人真自以为是 对不对
(LAUGHS)
(CHATTERING)
(CROWD CHEERING)
(LAUGHING)
我赢了
MAN: I win!
WOMAN: Please, sit.
请坐
把钱放在桌上我们就开始
Put your money on the table and we will begin.
Welcome. I am Madam Simza.
欢迎 我是西姆萨夫人
Cards can illuminate your past...
牌能洞悉你的过去
...clarify your present, and show you the future.
看清你的现状 揭示你的未来
If you have a specific question, hold it in your mind.
如果你想问什么问题 请在心中默念
HOLMES: Mm.
(SIGHS)
I'm holding.
我正在默念
Let me know when you're ready.
准备好了告诉我
说实话 我是想要算算
Actually, I'd prefer to read...
...your fortune.
你的命
Temperance inverted.
节制
逆位
Indicative of volatility.
意味着反覆无常
A woman who has recently taken her comfort in drink.
一个女人最近整天借酒浇愁
From what does she seek solace?
What does she not wish to see?
她在寻求什么慰藉 又在逃避什么东西
- A fool embarrassing himself?
- Hmm.
一个自以为是的傻瓜吗
- Oh, yes. The Fool.
哦 有了
愚者
某人误入歧途 身陷自己也不了解的事件
Someone has been led astray, involved
in something without their knowledge.
Not bad, but you have to make me believe you.
还不错 但是
你还不足以让我信服
I have to see it in your eyes.
再拿点诚意出来吧
- Right. I can do better.
- Uh-huh.
很好 我还能做得更好
The Two of Cups, a powerful bond.
圣杯之二 象征坚韧的纽带
But between whom? A brother and sister perhaps?
联系谁呢 也许是姐姐和弟弟吧
And I see a name. Yes, it's...
我能看到一个名字 没错 就是
...Rene.
芮内
What do you want?
你想要怎样
The Devil.
一张恶魔
Why are we playing this game?
你到底在玩什么花样
Where did you get this?
你从哪里得来的
I stole it from a woman in an auction room,
but I believe it was intended for you.
我从拍卖行一个女人那里偷来的
但我相信它是寄给你的
SIM (IN FRENCH):
亲爱的西姆
记住我的脸 因为你再也见不到它了
只有付出这样的代价
才能改变历史的进程
我终于找到我人生的意义
"Found my purpose in life."
找到我人生的意义
所以 我一直想问的问题是
So the question I've been holding
is, what purpose is Rene fulfilling?
芮内人生的意义是什么
(IN ENGLISH) Time is up.
时间到了
I have other clients.
我还有别的客人
Though you may not have detected
the wisp of astrakhan fur...
尽管我猜你可能还没发现我右肩上方的
木钉上挂着一缕俄国羊毛
...snagged on a nail over my left shoulder...
但是你一定不会没有闻到
...you couldn't have failed to notice
the overpowering aroma...
腌鲱鱼和伏特加的味道
...of herring pickled in vodka...
...in tandem with a truly unfortunate body odor.
以及那股浓重刺鼻的体味
There's a man concealed in the rafters above us.
我们头顶的房梁上躲着个人
A Cossack, renowned for their
infeasible acrobatic abilities...
哥萨克人 他们的运动能力举世闻名
一样出名的还有他们夜间的刺杀活动
...and are notorious for moonlighting as assassins.
So it's safe to presume that your
next client is here to kill you.
因此可以肯定你的下一个客人
是来杀你的
Anything else? No?
还想算什么吗 没了吗
HOLMES: First, pillage the nest.
首先 掏翻鸟窝
剪掉翅膀
Clip wings.
然后 猛击鸟嘴
Now blunt his beak.
敲碎鸟蛋
Crack eggs.
Scramble. Pinch of salt.
混匀 适量加盐
胡椒少许
Touch of pepper.
把煎蛋翻一面
Flip the omelet.
Additional seasoning required.
再加上必要的调味料
早饭做好了
Breakfast is served.
Come with me. I need you alive. Now.
跟我来 你可不能死 快
WOMAN: Oh!
(WOMAN GASPING)
(BAND PLAYING LIVELY MUSIC)
(LAUGHS)
(WOMEN SCREAMING)
Aah!
这一招你没算到吧
Didn't see that in the cards, did you?
CROWD: Oh...
(CROWD YELLING)
冷静点 伙计们
PUNTER: Coming down, folks, coming down.
Looks like we've got ourselves our next cockfight.
看样子我们又能再赌上一局了
(CROWD CHEERING)
五 四 三 二 一
Five, four, three, two, one...
...let him go!
放开他
(CROWD CHEERING)
PUNTER: Get up there!
追上去
(LAUGHS)
都是我的
All mine?
(CROWD YELLING)
(PEOPLE YELLING)
等一下
Now, wait a minute.
(CROWD YELLING)
(SPEAKS INDISTINCTLY)
(SIM PANTING)
你说得对 他确实很臭
You're right. He did stink.
嘿 你再跑啊
WATSON: Hey, you can run...
Where's you?
你在哪里
Just had a fight.
刚打了一架
- Just had a fight.
- Yes.
刚打了一架
没错
- Where were you?
- I'm glad to see...
你去哪儿了
看到你这个伴郎如此尽责我非常欣慰
...you're taking your best-man duties so seriously.
我寡不敌众
I was on my own! Not gonna get my monies!
我的钱都要不回来了
她还咬我的腿
She was biting my leg.
I'll have Carruthers put some fuel
into that motor carriage of yours.
我让卡罗瑟去给你们的汽车加点燃料
你们还有婚礼要参加
You do have a wedding to attend.
Oh, I'll drive.
我来开车
CARRUTHERS: Hmm.
(LAUGHS)
嘀嘀
Ho-honk. Ha-ha-ha.
我们再喝一杯嘛
WATSON: Let's have another drink.
- No, no, I think you've had quite enough.
不 我想你已经喝得够多了
(ENGINE BACKFIRES)
(BAGPIPES PLAYING LOUDLY)
(SNORING)
(SNORTS)
(CROWD APPLAUDING)
SOLDIER: Present arms!
(GLADSTONE BARKS)
(ENGINE STARTS)
我也来这里参加过婚礼
MAN: I've been to a wedding here before.
Funeral too.
还有葬礼
The professor wants to meet.
教授想见见你
考虑到最近发生的事情 他早该来找我了
I'd expected to hear from him sooner,
in light of recent events.
He was wondering if it'd be convenient for
you to come by the college this afternoon.
他想知道今天下午你可否去大学跑一趟
他的课四点结束
His lecture concludes at 4.
Looking forward.
非常乐意
One side, chummy.
让一让 兄弟
(HORN HONKS)
(ENGINE BACKFIRES)
(BELL TOLLING)
(CHATTERING)
(WOMAN SINGING IN GERMAN OVER SPEAKERS)
《渔夫之歌》 舒伯特 一八二六年
"Fischerweise," Schubert, 1826.
（德语）
(SPEAKS IN GERMAN)
放弃你那些愚蠢的伎俩
- "Give up your foolish trickery."
- "This fish you cannot cheat."
这条鱼不受欺骗
I hope I'm not intruding.
希望我没打扰你们
稍等片刻
Excuse me. Matthew, take these up to Mr. Williams.
马修 把这些带去交给威廉姆斯先生
And make sure he packs my white tie and tails.
让他记得带上我的白色领带和燕尾服
- I'll take care of it, professor.
- Thank you. I do apologize.
我知道了 教授
谢谢
真的很抱歉 我就要开始巡回演讲了
I'm off on a blasted lecture tour. Would
you care for some tea or coffee?
你想喝茶还是咖啡
- Neither.
- Something stronger, perhaps?
都不用
那来点烈性饮料吧
No, but might I trouble you for an inscription?
不了 但是能否麻烦您给我签个名
（《小行星动力学 及 课堂笔记》）
（詹姆斯-莫里亚蒂教授 着）
(MORIARTY SCRIBBLING)
I read that the good doctor was to be married today.
我听说那位好大夫今天结婚了
婚礼怎么样
How was the service?
Definitive.
圆满完成
He'll no longer be party to my investigations.
He's out of the equation.
他不再是我的侦查伙伴 没有半点干系
这一点相信你一定会充分考虑的
I trust you'll take this into consideration.
（《室内园艺的艺术》）
MORIARTY: And what considerations
will you grant me?
那你有没有为我考虑呢
Have you actually read the book?
你认真看过这本书吗
我觉得很有说服力
I found it compelling...
...though I'm primarily interested
in your more recent endeavors.
尽管我主要的兴趣还是你最近的工作
I take that as a compliment.
非常感谢你的赞美
I have the utmost regard for your talents.
我对你的才华也相当敬佩
It's a pleasure to finally meet you...
我很荣幸终于能和你
...officially.
正式见面了
HOLMES: Are you familiar with
the study of graphology?
不知你对笔迹学有没有研究
I've never given it any serious thought, no.
不 我没有太在意这个方面
The psychological analysis of handwriting.
对书写笔迹的心理分析
The upward strokes on the P, the J, and
the M indicate a genius-level intellect.
从你上半部分的Ｐ和Ｊ和Ｍ
可以看出智慧高人一等
While the flourishes on the lower zone...
而下半部分的华丽笔法则说明
...denote a highly creative yet meticulous nature.
你富于创造又非常严谨的天性
但如果把字体倾斜
和运笔的力度结合起来
But if one observes the overall slant
and the pressure of the writing...
就可以看出你这个人极度自恋
...there's a suggestion of acute narcissism,
a complete lack of empathy...
完全丧失同情心
- ...and a pronounced inclination toward...
- No.
并且严重倾向于
错
道德沦丧
...moral insanity.
In answer to your previous request regarding
Dr. Watson not being involved...
关于你之前提到的
华生大夫与此事无关的说法
...the answer is no.
我的回答是 错
The laws of celestial mechanics dictate
that when two objects collide...
天体运动的法则告诉我们
当两个物体碰撞时
...there is always damage of a collateral nature.
总会有些影响
波及到周边
举例来说
Exempli gratia.
Two gentlemen find themselves at cross-purposes.
两位男士 意见不合势同水火
年轻的女士 挣扎于两人之间
A young woman torn between them.
(GASPS THEN COUGHS)
这压力令她难以承受
The strain proves loo much for her,
and she suddenly falls ill...
她突然之间病倒
...with tragic consequences.
结果以悲剧收场
A rare form of tuberculosis.
一种罕见的结核病例
She succumbed in a matter of seconds.
短短数秒就夺去了她的生命
Now...
现在
...are you sure you want to play this game?
你确定要下这局棋吗
I'm afraid you'd lose.
恐怕你会输
Rest assured, if you attempt to bring
destruction down upon me...
不用担心 如果你想置我于死地
...I shall do the same to you.
我也不会心慈手软
My respect for you, Mr. Holmes, is
the only reason you're still alive.
我对你的敬重 福尔摩斯先生
是你活到现在的唯一原因
You've paid me several compliments.
你的好话说了不少
Let me pay you one in return...
我也有一言相告
...when I say that if I were assured
of the former eventuality...
如果我想要的结果可以达到的话
...I would cheerfully accept the latter.
我愿意付出任何代价
I'll be sure to send my regards to the happy couple.
我一定会向那对新人致以诚挚的问候
Another time, then.
改日再聚吧
(TRAIN HORN BLOWS)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
准备发车去布莱顿
CONDUCTOR: All aboard for Brighton! All aboard!
准备发车
Which coach are we?
哪个车厢来着
We should be just here.
我们应该就在这儿
(GASPS)
Ooh.
First class.
一等车厢
(MEN SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY)
CONDUCTOR: All aboard for Brighton! All aboard!
去布莱顿的列车即将发车
Hurry up, Dr. Watson, your wife needs you.
快上车 华生大夫 你的妻子需要你
Coming, Mrs. Watson.
这就来 华生太太
Ooh. First class, champagne.
一等车厢和香槟
You do know how to spoil a girl, Mr. Watson.
你真会讨女孩子欢心 华生先生
You're not just any girl.
你可不是普通女孩子
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
抱歉 夫人
I'm sorry, madam. You can't use the lavatory
while the train's in the station.
火车靠站期间不能使用洗手间
You're Mrs. Watson.
你可是华生太太
Give me that bottle.
把瓶子给我
John, there is nowhere else in
the world I would rather be.
这世界上除了你身边
我哪里也不想去
There's no one I'd rather be with.
我也只愿你一人陪在身边
Why do you have a gun stuffed down
the back of your trousers?
为什么你背后裤腰上会插着把枪呢
Heh. Old habits.
积习难改
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
Ahem. Come in.
请进
- Oh, yes, please.
- We didn't order that.
哦 好的 谢谢
我们没要这个
是我们附赠的 先生
With our compliments, sir.
Thank you. Put it there.
谢谢 放那里吧
(TRAIN HORN BLOWS)
Open the door, John.
打开车门 约翰
我想你可以出去了
I think it's time for you to leave.
坐下
Sit down.
Shh.
(BLOWS LANDING)
(GUN COCKS)
I agree it's not my best disguise, but I had to make do.
我知道这不算是我最好的伪装
但也只能凑合了
- My God.
- They'll be back.
我的天哪
他们会回来的
- John, shut the door.
- They'll only shoot through it.
约翰 快关门
他们隔着门也会开枪的 亲爱的
HOLMES: He's right, you know.
- Oh, my God.
他说得对
我的上帝呀
(GUNSHOT)
我很理解你
- I understand.
- Do you?
是吗
Terribly inconvenient.
确实造成很多不便
我们时间不多了
We don't have much time.
他们大概有多少人
- How many are we expecting?
- Half a dozen.
六七个吧
他们是谁
WATSON: Who are they?
- A wedding present from Moriarty.
莫里亚蒂送你的结婚礼物
Lovely ceremony, by the way. Many a tear shed in joy.
顺便说一句 婚礼很棒
大家流下了喜悦的泪水
MARY: Oh, John?
哦 约翰
(GUNSHOT)
稍等片刻 亲爱的
Yeah, just a minute, darling.
你相信我吗
- Do you trust me?
- No.
不
Well, then I shall have to do something about that.
既然如此我就得
有所表现才行
(MARY SCREAMS)
Who's up to bat next, you bastards?
谁想下一个受死 你们这群畜生
(GUNSHOT)
派点像样的人过来
Send out the fast bowler!
John, do shut the door.
约翰 把门关上吧
It had to be done.
我别无选择
She's safe now.
她现在安全了
In my own defense, I timed it perfectly.
你先听我说 我时机掌握得很好
Did you kill my wife?!
你杀死了我妻子
你居然杀死了我的新婚妻子
Did you just kill my new wife?!
Of course not!
当然没有
What do you mean? How do you know that
when you just threw her off a train?
什么意思 你刚把她扔下火车怎么会没事
我说了 时机掌握得很好
I told you, I timed it perfectly.
What does that mean?!
这是什么意思
- Calm down.
- Explain!
冷静点
回答我
By the time I've explained, we'd both be dead!
等我解释清楚我们也都死了
I'm sorry, madam. You can't use the lavatory
while the train's in the station.
抱歉夫人 火车靠站期间不能使用洗手间
（有人）
（磷 高度易燃）
(TRAIN HORN BLOWS)
（空闲）
(ALL COUGHING)
(MAN SCREAMS)
That was no accident.
这可不是巧合
It was by design.
是我设计好的
Now, do you need me to elaborate...
现在
你是要听我详细说明
...or can we just crack on?
还是我们先干正经事
Come on!
快来
(TRAIN HORN BLOWS)
Don't worry, old boy, she's as safe as houses.
别担心 老伙计
她现在很安全 正和我哥哥在一起
She's with my brother.
I'm on my honeymoon!
我正在度蜜月
Why did you lead them here?!
Why did you involve us?!
你为什么引他们过来
为什么要牵连我们
他们不是冲我来的而是冲你来的
They aren't here for me! They're here for you!
幸运的是
Fortunately...
...so am I.
我也来了
Now mind the door.
当心开门了
Good evening.
晚上好
I think you'll find that second
class is more comfortable.
我想你们会觉得二等车厢更加舒服
道路很畅通
The coast is clear.
To the south, quick march.
快点去 跑起来
(WOMAN WHIMPERS)
Lie down with me, Watson.
陪我躺一会儿 华生
- Why?
- I insist.
为什么
我执意如此
(GRUNTS)
What are we doing down here?
我们躺下来干什么
We are waiting. I am smoking.
我们在等待 而我在抽烟
- Patiently waiting.
- For what?
耐心地等待
等什么
Your window of opportunity.
让你反击的机会
(CLICKING)
Make it count.
不要失手
(SCREAMING)
I said make it count. How many
windows must I provide?
叫你不要失手
我要给你创造几个机会才够呢
(SCREAMING)
Who'd have known that honeymooning in
Brighton was such a dangerous notion?
谁会想到去布莱顿度蜜月会如此凶险
Is that what this is about?
你觉得是这个原因吗
By your own admission, you've never enjoyed it there.
你自己也承认 你并不喜欢那地方
I've never been to Brighton.
我就从来没去过布莱顿
Or you're just too fragile to remember at present.
还是你现在吓得想不起来了
哦 闭嘴
Oh, shut up.
Tell me my wife's safe.
告诉我我妻子没事
I can't do both.
这我不能同时办到
I promise. As I said, I timed it perfectly.
肯定没事 说了 我的时机掌握得很好
(MARY SCREAMS)
MYCROFT: Over here, madam!
到这儿来 夫人
I believe congratulations are in order, Mrs. Watson.
我应该要祝你新婚快乐 华生太太
我也叫福尔摩斯
I'm the other Holmes.
You mean there's two of you?
你是说有两个福尔摩斯吗
How marvelous. Could this evening get any better?
太棒了 今天晚上真是精彩极了
Why were Mary and I targeted at all?
为什么我和玛丽会成为目标
Excellent question. The answer is twofold.
问得好
这有两层原因
他盯上我们都是因为你
He's after us because of you.
在这件事上恐怕你也有一半责任
I'm afraid you must bear half the responsibility.
你又来了
- Here it comes. So predictable.
- Had you and Mary...
要不是你和玛丽
就知道会这样
...not been hell-bent on wedding,
we could've solved this case.
这么迫不及待要结婚
这案子早就搞定了
行行行 都怪我
- Oh, it's my fault now.
- The argument could be made...
我的意思是 你不得不承认
不 我不承认
- No, it couldn't.
- ...that your nuptials were poorly timed.
你婚礼办得实在不是时候
Thus, our relationship...
因此 我们的感情
Relationship?
什么感情
Very well, partnership.
那好吧 我们的友谊还没有走到尽头
...has not yet run its course.
My dear fellow, if you could be bothered
to see this through to the end...
我的朋友 如果你能帮我把这个案子了结
...I shall never again ask you to assist me.
我今后再也不来找你帮忙了
Once more unto the breach.
最后一次 下不为例
That's the spirit. Now, to the question.
就等你这句话
好 回到正题
This is so deliciously complicated.
You may be asking yourself...
案情复杂得让人欲罢不能
你可能会问自己 一个犯罪首脑会想要从
...what does a criminal mastermind want
with a simple gypsy fortune teller?
一个吉普赛占卜师那里得到什么
It's her brother, I tell you. When
we find him, and we must...
是想要她的弟弟 我告诉你
等我们找到这个关键人物
你先找到我的行李
After you find my luggage.
Go on.
去找吧
Wait.
等等
Where is it we're going?
我们这次要去哪儿
Paris, the most sensible honeymoon destination of all.
巴黎 全世界最佳的蜜月胜地
- So why Paris?
- Peaches.
为什么去巴黎
有桃子
Outside the city at Montreuil...
有一个以干果著称的吉普赛人营地
...there's a Gypsy camp famous for
its dried fruit, especially peaches.
桃子尤其出名
And there we shall find our fortune teller...
在那个地方应该能找到
那个占卜师 然后把包还给她
...and return her bag.
(SNIFFS)
（莫里亚蒂教授讲座）
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
这本书真是太棒了
谢谢您
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
(MAN 1 SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
您真是无与伦比
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
过奖了 谢谢
And my ticket?
那么 我的票呢
(MAN 2 SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
真是好书
谢谢
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
（《唐璜》 巴黎大剧院）
Unfortunately, you won't be needing yours.
很不幸 你的票可能用不上了
That's a shame, professor. I was
looking forward to Don Giovanni.
太可惜了 教授
我一直很想去看《唐璜》
谢谢
(MAN 3 & MORIARTY SPEAK IN FRENCH)
Follow Meinhard.
跟着迈哈德
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
(MAN SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
(SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY)
(HORSE NEIGHING)
(MEN YELLING)
(VIOLIN PLAYING LIVELY MUSIC)
谢谢 停
(WATSON SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
(WATSON WHISTLES TWICE)
Wake up, we're here.
醒一醒 我们到了
Brace yourself. We're about to be violated.
做好准备 我们就要被调戏了
别这么杞人忧天
Don't be so cynical.
你好 我找 西姆萨
(SPEAKING IN FRENCH)
哦 知道 先生 我知道 她在呢
对 她在 在
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
太好了 太好了
他们拿走了我的行李
- They're taking my luggage.
- Laugh them away, Watson. I have her bag.
你不用担心 华生 她的包在我这儿
她的包在我这儿
(SPEAKING IN FRENCH)
(LAUGHS)
她的包也拿走了
WATSON: You had her bag.
Now they have my coat.
现在外套也被拿走了
Where is Madam Simza?
西姆萨夫人在哪儿
(SPEAKING IN FRENCH)
(LAUGHS)
TAMAS: This is Simza.
这就是西姆萨
(GOOSE SQUAWKING)
(LAUGHS)
Sim is a goose.
西姆是只鹅
(CROWD CHUCKLING)
I am Sim. Ha-ha-ha.
我是西姆
Nice scarf. I like.
围巾不错 我喜欢
(HENS CLUCKING)
(CHUCKLING)
此事有关他的弟弟
(IN FRENCH)
- You hungry?
- (IN ENGLISH) Famished.
你饿不饿
饥饿难耐
Madam, this is a glorious hedgehog goulash.
夫人 这道刺猬肉炖杂菜太美味了
I can't remember ever having had better.
我不记得有吃过比这更好的
Do tell me, when was the last time
you had a hedgehog goulash?
告诉我
你上次吃刺猬肉炖杂菜是什么时候
I told you, Watson, I can't remember.
我说了 华生 我不记得了
(WHISPERINGS) Perhaps you've repressed it.
也许你只是在压抑
(CHUCKLES)
That's where we differ. Unlike you, I repress nothing.
我和你不一样 我从不压抑
(IN NORMAL VOICE) Perfectly normal.
再正常不过了
How dare you be rude to this woman
who has invited us into her tent...
你怎么可以对一个邀请我们进她的帐篷
...offered us her hedgehog?
又给我们刺猬吃的女士如此无礼
Says the man who throws women from trains.
作为把女士推下火车的人你有资格吗
你们是什么人
Who are you two?
热心的公民
Concerned citizens.
Why did someone try to kill me?
为什么有人想要杀我
你弟弟结交了一个非常危险的人物
Your brother has become involved
with a very dangerous man...
他确信芮内告诉了
你一些不该透露的事情
...who clearly believes that Rene has told
you something you shouldn't know.
我什么都不知道
I don't know anything.
我找他找了一年多时间
I've been looking for him for over a year.
这就是我为什么会去伦敦
That was why I was in London.
- It's the last place anyone saw him.
- It's clear that your brother loves you.
那是他最后一次出现的地方
显然你弟弟很爱你
他绝对不会寄一些会对你不利的邮件
He'd never send you a message that
would put you in harm's way.
Any information, therefore, would
be, by default, unintentional.
因此透漏的信息都是由于疏忽大意
Has he sent you anything else?
他有寄给你其他东西吗
Just a few drawings.
只有几张画而已
Let's just see what they have to tell us.
让我们来看看里面的奥妙
Unusual choice of paper. Thicker gauge,
designed for a printing press.
没选用一般的画纸
比较厚 是印刷厂专用的
- And it's the same stock as the letter.
- Mm.
这些纸的质地和信纸一样
They smell musty.
闻起来有霉味
Must have been stored somewhere cold and damp.
一定是存放在阴冷潮湿的地方
What's that? Blood?
那是什么 血迹吗
Wine. So a wine cellar located near a printing press.
红酒 一个靠近印刷厂的红酒酒窖
That should narrow it down.
范围缩小了
他说他再也不会回去的
(IN FRENCH)
There's a wine cellar used by the
anarchist group Lapin Vert.
一个叫绿兔子的无政府组织有个酒窖
Rene was close to their leader.
芮内和他们的老大曾很有交情
Claude Ravache.
克劳德-哈瓦锡
- A bomb maker.
- I sampled some of his work last week.
炸弹专家
我上个星期才见过他的作品
I was a part of the movement. So was Rene.
我曾是那组织的成员
芮内也是
Until it became too extreme for us.
后来我们觉得它太极端了
Ravache knows me.
哈瓦锡认识我
If my brother's back there, he will see us.
如果我弟弟回去了 他会见我们的
We will send a message.
我们这就去问他
我去约哈瓦锡见面
好
(SIM SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
无论如何 吉普赛人劝你喝酒你都别喝
Whatever you do, don't let these
gypsies make you drink.
知道
Of course.
You dance?
跳舞吗
For God's sake, don't dance. It'll be the death of you.
看在上帝的份上别跳 不然你就死定了
You know what happens when you dance.
你知道跳舞是什么下场吗
(BAND PLAYING LIVELY MUSIC)
Huuh...
Oh, good morning, Mrs. Watson.
早上好 华生太太
- Have you had breakfast?
- I...
早饭吃过了吗
Stanley here does a wonderful deviled kidney.
斯坦利做的辣烤羊腰棒极了
(TRAY RATTLING)
MARY: Ahem.
- Carruthers?
- Morning, sir.
卡罗瑟
早安 先生
Telegram for Mrs. Watson.
有华生太太的电报
Uh...
It just doesn't make any sense.
我一点也看不懂
Allow me.
乐意效劳
Oh, yes.
有了
"My most loathed Mary, I do not love
you. I never wish to see you again.
我最厌恶的玛丽
我一点也不爱你 再也不想见你了
离开你的每一秒钟都是祝福
Every moment I count away from you is a blessing."
Fret not. It's a double encryption, my dear...
别担心
这是双重密码 亲爱的
...that Sherly and I have used since we were boys.
我和歇利小时候就开始用了
If the first letter of the message is a consonant...
如果信息的第一个字母是个辅音
...then what follows is the mirrored truth.
那信息的真实含义就和表述相反
- I see.
- Hmm.
好吧
Stanley!
斯坦利
You know, although our time together
has been but a brief interlude...
我说 尽管我们相处的时间非常短
...I'm beginning to understand how
a man of particular disposition...
但我开始理解为什么
有着某些特点的男性
...under certain circumstances,
extreme ones perhaps...
在某些特殊情况下 或许是极端情况下
...might grow to enjoy the company of...
会变得喜欢身边有一个
- ...a person of your gender. Hmm.
- Hmm.
像你这样性别的人
Thank you so much.
非常感谢
Most charming.
你过奖了
May...? Terribly sorry. Thank you.
不好意思 谢谢
Where are you going, Stanley?
你要去哪里啊 斯坦利
(BELL TOLLING)
(HOOVES PATTERING)
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
DRIVER: Whoa, whoa.
（七蛙餐厅）
(SPEAKING IN FRENCH)
你们到了 下车吧
跟我来
(SPEAKING IN FRENCH)
进来进来
(CHATTERING)
Still hiding in basements?
还躲在地下室吗
RAVACHE (IN FRENCH):
最近这阵子不方便出去
能见到你我很高兴
I'm not here to see you.
我不是来看你的
(IN ENGLISH) Yeah.
来吧
RAVACHE (IN FRENCH):
我很想将这一时刻
(IN ENGLISH) ...with your English friends.
与你的英国朋友分享
1189, a seminal vintage.
一七八九年 很有意义的年份
The year of our glorious revolution.
那是我们大革命的一年
- Is he here?
- When freedom triumphed over tyranny.
他在这儿吗
自由战胜暴政的一年
Is my brother here?
我弟弟在吗
I haven't seen him for a long time.
我很久没见过他了
You're lying.
你在撒谎
Sit, please.
请坐
A letter was received from Rene using this same paper.
芮内寄来的信纸和这儿的一样
Of course. He took it with him wherever he went.
那当然 他去哪里都随身携带
He's telling the truth. Rene isn't here.
他没骗你 芮内不在这儿
- He was given another assignment by an...
- An anonymous benefactor.
他的任务是去协助一个
一个不具名的赞助人
Another Englishman...
另一个英国人
...with money, power, who supported our cause.
他有钱 有权 支持我们的事业
And now...
而现在
...he dictates our every move...
我们全都要听他的
...demanding I take responsibility for his acts of terror.
却要我为他的恐怖袭击负责
I made a deal with the devil.
我和恶魔定了契约
But after tonight, ahem...
但过了今晚
...it will be over.
一切就结束了
My job is almost done.
我的任务快完成了
He's had you plant another bomb, hasn't he?
他又让你放了个炸弹 对不对
SIM: Claude, please.
克劳德 告诉他们
These men can help you.
他们俩可以帮助你
I wish they could.
我也希望他们可以
You see, gentlemen...
知道吗 先生们
...he has my wife and children.
我老婆和孩子在他手上
If you tell us where the bomb is...
如果你告诉我炸弹在哪里
- ...I'll find a way to help your family.
- That's already taken care of.
我会想办法救你的家人
这事不用你操心了
We have a deal.
我们都说好了
He and I.
我和他
No loose ends.
不留后患
There's only one thing I can do to keep my family safe.
要保证我家人安全我只有一个选择
- You have less than 10 minutes.
- Don't!
你们只剩不到十分钟时间了
不要
(GUNSHOT)
(SPEAKING IN FRENCH)
发生什么了 走 去看看 快
(EXHALES)
He has no further need of that pistol. Why
don't you take it and cover the stairs?
那手枪对他没用 不如你拿来掩护楼梯
(MEN YELLING)
快去看看 快
这个地方就一个出口
WATSON: There's only one way out of this place.
Right you are.
你说得对
Ah. Ingenious.
别具匠心
That's the one. Quickly as we can.
就是这个 我们快走吧
You know what to do with that sandbag, Watson.
你知道该如何处理那个沙袋 华生
Quick now.
快点
(MEN YELLING)
快下去看看
Doctor, could you secure that lever?
大夫 请确认一下那个拉杆
You could have told me.
你早该告诉我
Ravache was strong. He lived for liberty.
He would never take his own life.
哈瓦锡很坚强
他为自由而生 不会轻易自杀的
WATSON: Calm yourself.
冷静一点
My brother, he's weak.
我弟弟 他很脆弱
Sim, I need you to take a deep breath...
西姆 你先深吸一口气
...and follow us.
（皇帝）
然后跟着我们
To the opera.
快去大剧院
(SINGING IN ITALIAN)
(INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE)
（商业峰会 迈哈德下榻凯旋门大酒店）
（凯旋门大酒店）
I was mistaken.
我想错了
- What?
- I made a mistake.
什么
我犯了个错误
(MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
(IN FRENCH)
尽管政治上我们有分歧
商业让我们团结
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
(SINGING IN ITALIAN)
(CROWD YELLING)
He took the shot from here.
他选在这个位置
Using a tripod and a shooting stick.
还用了三脚架和枪托
然后意识到还有个更好的位置
And realized there was a better position.
There's a faint scrape where he dragged
his tripod and set it up here.
这道浅痕说明他把三脚架拖到了这里
- Six hundred yards? WATSON: Or 650?
大概六百码吧
或者六百五十码
HOLMES: Not to mention a seven-
or eight-mile-an-hour wind.
更别提还有时速七 八英哩的风
He would've needed a wind gauge.
他还得要个风速计
Which he placed here.
就放在这里
HOLMES: And put a cigarette down here.
还在这里放了根香烟
SIM: Can anyone shoot that far?
这么远能打中吗
Not more than half a dozen men in all of Europe.
这种人整个欧洲不过五六个
How many of those men served in Afghanistan?
这些人有几个参加过阿富汗战争
WATSON: Why?
- Hirschsprung with a touch of Tekel.
怎么
赫什朋加泰克尔的混合烟草
Must have fallen out when he was rolling up.
肯定是卷烟的时候掉下来的
Wasn't that the blend you all smoked?
你们军队都是抽这种的吧
- Didn't I read something about a colonel?
- Sebastian Moran.
我听说过某个上校的事
塞巴斯汀-莫兰
Best marksman in the British army.
英国陆军的头号神枪手
Dishonorable discharge.
行为不检革除军籍
He's likely now a gun for hire. This is the second
victim of his that I've encountered.
现在可能当职业杀手了
这是我遇到的第二个他的受害者
WATSON: What better way to conceal a killing?
还有什么能更好地掩盖谋杀
No one looks for a bullet hole in a bomb blast.
没人会在爆炸现场去找弹孔
- He's 20 minutes late.
- He must come soon.
迟到了二十分钟
肯定快到了
I don't have any papers.
我身上可没证件
WATSON: And I am a foreigner.
我又是个外国人
这种局面就是莫里亚蒂最想要的
This climate is exactly what Moriarty wants.
Ahem. The omelet fines herbes was divine...
香草煎蛋 很好吃
...but they spared every expense on the tea.
但这儿的茶简直太次了
Now shall we compare moods,
or consider what we know?
现在我们是继续抱怨还是先理清思路
Last night's bombing was clearly meant...
昨天的爆炸显然想让人以为是
...to look like Germany's retaliation for Strasbourg.
德国对斯特拉斯堡事件的报复
However, the bomb was also meant to
conceal the murder of just one man.
但真正目的是
掩饰一起针对个人的谋杀案
The man killed by the gunshot was
none other than Alfred Meinhard.
被枪杀的男人就是阿尔弗雷德-迈哈德
Ah.
He makes guns. Big guns.
他是军火商 重型军火
Only days ago, a large share of his company
was bought by an unknown investor.
几天前某不明投资人
买了他公司大量股票
Moriarty.
莫里亚蒂
The clues point in one direction, but to
avoid repeating last night's debacle...
线索提示了一个方向
但为了避免重蹈昨晚的覆辙
...I was obliged to collect more sufficient
data, hence my tardiness.
我有必要收集够充分的证据
所以我来迟了
（欧洲和平进程受挫）
（凯旋门大酒店发生爆炸）
Train departs in 40 minutes, sir.
离开车还有四十分钟 先生
WAITER: Whoa!
(HOLMES SNIFFS)
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
先生 你的外套 谢谢
- Just the bags.
- But...
你拿行李就行了
但是
We have enough time for me to indulge my little habit.
我还有时间来满足一下我的兴趣爱好吧
Yes.
是的
HOLMES: His habit of feeding that
urban species, the feral pigeon.
他的兴趣爱好就是去喂那些城里的鸽子
So there are seven mainline railway stations in Paris.
巴黎有七个主干线火车站
But taking 10 minutes to get
to the Jardin des Tuileries...
但能让他花个十分钟跑去杜乐丽花园
...where the largest concentration of
the winged vermin may be found...
去找那群长着翅膀的寄生虫
...reduces there to one, the Gare du Nord...
就只有一种可能 巴黎北站
...where he will be just in time to
catch the 11:04 train to Berlin.
他正好可以赶上
十一点零四分开往柏林的火车
It makes several stops along
the way, one of which is...
这趟车沿路会停几站 其中就有
Heilbronn.
海尔布隆
Exactly where we must go.
正是我们要去的地方
Where Meinhard's factory is.
迈哈德的工厂 就在那里
HOLMES: It's Moriarty's factory now.
现在是莫里亚蒂的工厂了
Unfortunately, due to the bombing...
很遗憾 由于爆炸
法德两国间的通道关闭了
...the crossing between France
and Germany is to be closed.
I'm afraid our pursuit is over unless
we can happen upon a comrade...
本案的追查到此结束 除非我们碰巧遇到
...who knows their way around borders.
一位很熟悉边境地形的同伴
Too English.
太英国了
However, you do make a fantastic gypsy.
不过你确实很像吉普赛人
Certainly smell like a fantastic gypsy.
浑身散发着吉普赛的味道
Now, now, no need to be demeaning.
你没必要这么损
It is a nice scarf.
这是你的漂亮围巾
No, no, too English. It'll suit you more.
不 太英国了 比较适合你
(SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
谢谢
Black one is yours. Gray one is mine.
黑马是你的 灰马是我的
- And this is for you.
- Um... Hmm.
这匹马是你的
Right.
对了
- Where are the wagons?
- The wagon is too slow.
马车呢
马车太慢了 你不会骑吗
Can't you ride?
(HORSE GRUNTS)
It's not that he can't ride.
不是他不会骑马
How is it you put it, Holmes?
你怎么解释的
They're dangerous at both ends
and crafty in the middle.
这种动物两头都危险 中间又麻烦
Why would I want anything with a mind of
its own bobbing about between my legs?
我不想要一个有自我意识的东西
在我的两腿间上下耸动
Then I shall require a bicycle, thank you very much.
那我就要一辆自行车吧 非常感谢
It's 1891. Could've chartered a balloon.
都一八九一年了 就该租一个热气球
How can we make this more manageable?
有没有简单点的办法
HOLMES: Where's the fire?
火烧眉毛了吗
(HOLMES WHIMPERING)
HOLMES: It's not as if Germany is going somewhere.
德国又不会逃走的
We know another way.
还有另一条路
HOLMES: Slow and steady wins the race.
坚持不懈才会胜利
(HORSES NEIGHING)
(RIDERS YELLING)
(HOLMES WHISTLING)
HOLMES: Come on!
快来
WATSON: We slip in through the loading
bay, find out what he's doing...
我们从卸货码头溜进去
找到他的把柄
...and we get out.
然后溜出来
Getting out might be tricky.
溜出来有点难度
We will get you out.
我们会来接应你们
If my brother's in there, get him out alive.
如果我弟弟在里面 带他活着出来
(SOLDIERS CHATTERING)
Are you happy?
你开心吗
- What?
- At this moment...
什么
在此时此刻
...are you as happy as you would be
on your honeymoon in Brighton?
你是不是和去布莱顿度蜜月一样开心
I'm not going to grace that question with an answer.
我根本懒得去回答这个问题
- Are you happy?
- I think we're here for another reason.
你开心吗
我认为我们来这儿是有其他原因的
- Okay.
- Shall we get on...?
好吧
让我们开始做
- Simple question.
- Will we do something?
这并不难回答
我们是去办正经事
- Or wait for them to come back round?
- What time is it?
还是在这里等他们转回来
现在几点
- Three-fifteen.
- Over there...
三点十五分
在这个设施的居住区里应该有个电报室
...in the residential part of the complex
should be a telegraph office.
Send this to Mycroft. Be back here on the hour.
把这个发给迈克罗夫特 整点时回这里来
（迈哈德邮政与电报局）
（电报局）
(DOG BARKING IN DISTANCE)
(GUARDS CHATTERING)
(LIQUID BUBBLING)
(SNIFFS)
（德国）
（斯德哥尔摩 赫尔辛基 莫斯科）
（荷兰）
（海尔布隆）
MORAN: That's what you get, Mr. Holmes,
when industry marries arms.
当工业与武器联姻 这就是它们的产物
Now put your gun down.
把你的枪放下
It's a bit old-fashioned.
它已经过时了
What you need is one of these.
你应该搞一把这种枪
Go on.
去拿吧
Pick one.
挑一把
Machine pistol, self-repeating.
机关手枪
自动连发
Takes 1.63 caliber rounds...
使用了七点六三口径的子弹
...in one of these.
装在这里面
A 10-shot box magazine.
荷载十发子弹的盒式弹匣
- Easy enough to load.
- Hmm.
装填十分方便
I'd imagine one would have to retract
the bolt to engage the first round.
我估计要拉一下枪栓才能让子弹上膛
Easier done than said.
比说得还简单
Take him to the surgery.
把他送去手术室
I'll find the doctor.
我去把医生找来
"Come at once if convenient.
如果方便的话请来一趟
If inconvenient, come all the same."
如果不方便 也请来一趟
(SNIFFS)
MAN: This is schnapps.
这是杜松子酒
MORIARTY: A telegram was sent from here.
你在这里发了个电报
(HOLMES CLEARS THROAT)
This isn't schnapps, it's aquavit,
distilled from potato mash.
这不是杜松子酒 是阿夸维特
是从土豆泥里蒸馏出来的
A common misconception. Thank you, by the way.
经常有人会弄错 不过还是谢谢了
Who was it sent to?
电报发给谁了
My horror at your crimes is matched only...
我对你的罪行恐惧之至 就如同
...by my admiration at the skill it took to achieve them.
我对你实施罪行时的技巧钦佩至极
Who was it sent to?
电报发给谁了
HOLMES: You used the anarchists and their
bombs to create a crisis in Europe...
你利用无政府主义者和他们的炸弹
在欧洲各国间制造了一个又一个危机
...nation against nation
Under various pseudonyms, you bought,
schemed, or murdered your way...
你用多个假名收买算计甚至
通过谋杀来渗透各行各业
...into numerous industries, assuring that
none of it could be traced to you.
却不留下与你有关的蛛丝马迹
Cotton, opium, steel, now arms
and chemical weaponry.
棉花 鸦片 钢铁 以及军火和化学武器
All to be shipped across Europe in less than a week.
所有东西一周之内就能运到欧洲各地
Everything from bullets to bandages.
从子弹到绷带一应俱全
Now that you own the supply, you
intend to create the demand.
既然已掌握了供给
你就打算创造需求了
A world war.
一场世界大战
(TAPPING)
MORIARTY: You are familiar with Schubert's work.
你很熟悉舒伯特的作品
(GUNS COCK)
站住 别动
(GUARD SPEAKS IN GERMAN)
The Trout is perhaps my favorite.
《鳟鱼》 可能是我的最爱
快跪下
(SPEAKS IN GERMAN)
一个渔夫急于抓住一条狡猾的鱼
A fisherman grows weary of trying
to catch an elusive fish.
Out the way, out the way.
快让开 快让开
So he muddies the water.
所以他搅浑河水
I'm warning you.
我警告你哦
Confuses the fish.
迷惑了那条鱼
别耍花招
(GUNSHOTS)
You were warned.
警告过你的
It doesn't realize until too late
that it has swum into a trap.
等它发现自己进入陷阱的时候已经太迟
(GRUNTING)
(HOLMES YELLS THEN GROANS)
(ELECTRICITY BUZZING)
(FEEDBACK SQUEALS)
(SCHUBERT'S "DIE FORELLE"
PLAYING OVER SPEAKERS)
（歌词大意）
明亮的小溪里 有一条鳟鱼
(MORIARTY SINGING "DIE FORELLE")
它纵情欢乐 穿梭如箭
我站在小溪旁 静静地观望
在清澈的溪水里 它游得多欢畅
(GUNSHOT)
(MUSIC CONTINUES PLAYING)
(HOLMES SCREAMING)
(HOLMES SCREAMING OVER SPEAKERS)
(GUNSHOT)
(MUSIC STOPS)
Let's try this again, shall we?
我们再试一次 好吗
To whom did you send the telegram?
那封电报你发给谁了
To my...
给我的
(GRUNTING)
(HOLMES GASPS)
To my brother Mycroft.
给我的哥哥迈克罗夫特
What are you playing at?
你这是在玩什么
That's not fair.
太不公平了
I've just got one more question for you.
我最后还有一个问题要问你
Which one of us is the fisherman...
我们两个谁是渔夫
...and which the trout?
谁是鳟鱼
Holmes?
福尔摩斯
- Holmes? HOLMES: Unh.
Take your time. Take your time.
不着急 慢慢找
(HOLMES GROANS)
Uh...
(GRUNTS)
Always good to see you, Watson.
见到你总是很高兴 华生
- What were you thinking?
- Wait.
你是想找死吗
等等
Wait?
等什么
Well, if you must know, I was thinking
I had him right where I wanted him.
告诉你吧 我想我抓到他了
就在我想抓他的地方
Right. Crack on, then.
好了 继续吧
Professor.
教授
I'm all right, I'm all right.
我没事 我没事
Don't waste time attending to me.
别浪费时间来帮我
(SHOUTING IN FRENCH)
还愣着干什么
快追 追
I'll find them. I'll find them.
我要抓住他们
(SIM WHISTLES)
Turn in three, two, one.
转身倒数 三 二 一
Come on, hurry up!
快点过来
MARKO: Go!
走
(MEN YELLING)
快 快
SIM: Did you see my brother? HOLMES:
No, but I'm certain he's been here.
找到我弟弟了吗
没有 但他肯定来过这里
WATSON: Where are we going?
- Over that wall.
我们该往哪儿走
去围墙那里
- How did you know I'd find you?
HOLMES: You didn't find me.
福尔摩斯 你怎么知道我找得到你
你没在找我 你是在用塔楼砸我
You collapsed a building on me.
(SOLDIERS SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
动作快点 赶快
谁他妈让你们把墙给轰了
(SOLDIERS CONTINUE SHOUTING)
WATSON: Where are the horses?
- They're behind.
马在哪里
在后面
- We need them.
- You wanna go back?
我们需要它们
你想回去吗
What's our way out?
退路在哪里
That's our way out.
退路在那里
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWING)
(SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
你们这群蠢货
谁他妈让你们把墙给轰了
赶快给我追 快点
别让他们跑了 快给我追
快 快点 追
(IN GERMAN)
如果让他们跑了
你们就等死吧
(IN GERMAN)
迫击炮手准备
(SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
准备开火 对准目标
(GRUNTS)
轮到小汉塞尔上场了
(SHOUTS IN GERMAN)
开火
(COUGHS)
(GRUNTING)
(GUARD SHOUTS IN GERMAN)
把手举起来
(GRUNTS)
(TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWING)
SIM: Go! Go!
快 快
WATSON: Come on!
快上去
(PANTS)
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
(GUNSHOT)
Marko! Marko!
马可 马可
(SIGHS)
(SIM SINGING IN ROMANI)
He's not breathing.
他没有呼吸了
Cradle his head.
抱住他的头
Raise his legs.
把脚抬起来
你千万别给我死了
Bloody well not gonna die on me.
(WATSON GRUNTING)
I'm not gonna make this easy on you.
我不会对你手下留情的
Come on. Come on.
呼吸
Come on.
(GRUNTING)
呼吸
I know you can hear me, you selfish bastard.
我知道你听得见的 自私的畜生
Come on!
呼吸啊
I know you can hear me, you bastard.
我知道你听得见的 自私的畜生
(SIGHS)
His wedding gift.
他的结婚礼物
(SCREAMING)
妈呀
HOLMES: Terrible dream.
噩梦啊
You, Mary, Gladstone and I were in a restaurant.
你 玛丽 格莱斯顿和我在餐厅吃饭
That satanic pony was there as well,
a massive fork in his hoof...
那只矮脚马也在那里
蹄子上拿了把大叉子想要吃了我
...and he turned on me!
What have you administered?
你打了什么药
Your wedding present.
你的结婚礼物
Who's been dancing on my chest?!
谁在我胸口上跳过舞
ME.
我
Why is my ankle so itchy?
为什么我脚踝那么痒
You have a large piece of wood sticking out of it.
因为有一大块的碎木片插在它上面
Good Lord. You, Tamas.
我的天哪 嘿 塔马斯
I have an important job to discuss
with you. Remind me of it later.
我有件重要的事情要和你说
记得等会儿提醒我
Sit down. Drink this.
坐下 把这个喝了
I need to get that out before it turns septic.
我要在出现败血症前把它取出来
- Did you call me "selfish bastard"?
- Probably.
你是不是骂我自私的畜生
有可能
Just leave it in. Leave it...!
还是别拔了 别拔了
(GROANS)
You are a...
你这家伙简直是
- Oh, you are some sort of...
- Be nice.
别惹我
(SIGHS)
I'm sorry you didn't get to Brighton.
我很遗憾你没去成布莱顿
Me too.
我也是
- I think we should go home.
- I concur.
我们该回家了
我同意
We're going home.
我们回家吧
Via Switzerland.
顺路去趟瑞士
What better place to start a war than a peace summit?
想挑起战争的最佳地点
就是和平峰会
We'll drop in and see my brother.
I'm sure he's missed you. Hm?
我们正好去看我哥哥 他一定很想你
I don't understand why you don't cancel the summit.
我还是不理解你为何不取消这次峰会
Fact is it's gonna happen whether we like it or not.
事实是无论我们怎么想它都会召开
Everyone has already arrived.
所有政要都到齐了
Although these gentlemen may be talking peace...
这些先生们或许在谈和平
...believe me, they're readying their armies at home.
相信我 他们都做好了战争的准备
To cancel the summit now would
be tantamount to war.
现在取消峰会就等于宣告战争
- The telegram, wasn't it clear?
- We have doubled the security, sir.
那封电报还不够清楚吗
我们增加了一倍的警力 先生
Oh, doubled security. That's comforting.
双倍的警力 真叫人安心
You don't understand the delicacy of the situation.
你还不明白现在的情况有多微妙
I passed the telegram on to my superiors.
我把电报交给了我的上级 但他们就是
But they brought Moriarty in to advise
on the peace process in the first place.
一开始把莫里亚蒂拉来当和平顾问的人
He has positioned himself brilliantly.
他现在的身份很有优势
He's one of our foremost intellectuals,
a personal friend...
他是我国最重要的智囊 又是现任首相的
现任首相的私交好友 这个我们都知道
Of the prime minister. Yes, we all know that.
I believe you, but where's your evidence?
我相信你 但你的证据在哪里
He's too good to leave evidence.
他厉害到从不留下证据
He doesn't leave loose ends.
办事滴水不漏
SIM: Oh, he's alive.
他还活着
歇利 快放下
Sherly, put that down.
What is this contraption? May I have
it? The effect is most invigorating.
这个装置有什么用 给我好吗
吸了以后真有点兴奋
That's my private and personal supply
of oxygen, and you're not to touch it.
那是我私人专用的氧气储备 你不要乱碰
This argument is getting us nowhere.
这么讨论下去没有意义
I've arranged for documents to be prepared
which allow you into the ball. Carruthers.
我准备了一些文件让你们可以参加舞会
卡罗瑟
Stanley, Stanley.
斯坦利 斯坦利
You haven't aged a day. Is that my favorite chutney?
你一点都没有变 这是我最爱的甜辣酱吗
Fact is, we don't really know what he's planning.
问题是 我们还没弄清楚他的计划
SIM: It won't be another bomb.
WATSON: No, it wouldn't be.
不会再用炸弹了
这次不会用炸弹的
SIM: It doesn't make sense.
那样做没有意义
Why would he attack all the
nations only to unite them?
袭击所有国家 只会令他们团结
It'll be an assassination.
应该会有暗杀
By alone gunman at close range.
被一个孤胆枪手近身刺杀
Rene.
芮内
Unfortunately, yes.
很不幸 是他
- You knew.
- I had my suspicions.
你都知道
我之前只是怀疑
But having seen who would be
attending, I'm now certain.
但在看过出席名单后我就确定了
MYCROFT: Well, at least we know who to look out for.
现在起码知道该防着谁了
Rene will be the evidence.
芮内就是证据
If we can find him and stop him, we
will perhaps not only save his life...
如果能找到他 阻止他
我们可能不止救了他的命
...but prevent the collapse of Western civilization.
还避免了西方文明的崩溃
No pressure.
别有压力
Welcome, ambassador.
欢迎 大使先生
Professor James Moriarty.
詹姆斯-莫里亚蒂教授
(WALTZ MUSIC PLAYING OVER SPEAKERS)
MYCROFT: Now we're all present...
既然大家都到了 我就告诉你们
...I can tell you that the targets are the German
chancellor and his ambassador...
本次的主角是德国总理和他的大使
还有法国首相和他的手下
...the French prime minister and his man.
And the other nations are really working out
which side to take should hostilities erupt.
其他国家实际上是来
判断一旦开战应该站在哪一边
Prince Michael, a cousin of the czar,
and the Russian ambassador.
那是迈克尔王子 沙皇的表亲
和俄国大使
大公爵卡尔-路威格和奥匈帝国大使
The Archduke Karl Ludwig and the
Austro-Hungarian ambassador.
The Romanian Prime Minister and his ambassador.
罗马尼亚首相和他的大使
And of course our prime minister
and the British ambassador.
当然 还有我们的首相和英国大使
He'll choose a moment when the dignitaries
are assembled, preferably standing still.
他应该会选一个所有政要到齐的时候
最好是站着不动
Is there to be an official photograph?
有没有安排拍集体照
Indeed, yes. In 38 minutes.
当然 有的
还有三十八分钟
In which case, we might as well dance.
既然如此 我们不如跳个舞
I've never done this before.
我从来没跳过这个
Just follow my lead.
跟我跳就行了
- What do you see?
- Everything.
你看到了什么
一切
(GUESTS CHATTERING)
That is my curse.
这就是我的不幸
But you don't see what you're looking for.
可你没看到你要找的
I thought you'd never ask.
以为你不会请我了
Over my shoulder.
在我肩膀后面
Young man, German uniform, ceremonial sword.
年轻人 穿德国制服 带仪式佩剑
Got him.
看到了
HOLMES: Professional opinion?
有什么专业意见
WATSON: Trauma.
伤痕
Major injury.
受过重创
But excellent repair work.
但整形手术很成功
Dr. Hoffmanstahl.
是霍芬斯塔大夫
HOLMES: You did say he was at the
forefront of a medical innovation.
你说过他是医学创新的开拓者
We've already seen an example of his skills.
我们其实已经见过他的杰作了
Those twins weren't twins.
那两个人不是双胞胎
My suspicions were aroused in Heilbronn...
在海尔布隆时我产生了怀疑
...when one failed to go to the aid of the other.
一个中枪倒地另一个却不帮忙
I also noticed the discreet but unmistakable
puckering behind the ear...
我还注意到他耳后
有块隐蔽却独特的皱褶
...where his skin had been drawn
back. I should've realized then...
那里的皮肤被拉过
我当时就该意识到他们是手术的实验品
...that they were a surgical experiment.
To see if it is possible to make
one man look like another.
试验能不能让一个人长得就像另一个人
HOLMES: His face is no longer his own.
他的脸已经不是他自己的了
What better way to guarantee his world
war than to make the assassin...
确保世界大战发生的
最好办法就是让刺客
One of the ambassadors.
成为一名大使
(MUFFLED GRUNTING)
That narrows down the possibility to one of six.
这就把范围缩小为六人中的一个
You and Sim shall find her brother.
你和西姆定能找出她弟弟 我毫不怀疑
- Of this I have no doubt.
- Holmes.
福尔摩斯
You know my methods.
你知道我的计划
And I know where you'll be.
我也知道你要去哪里
No possible solution could be more
congenial to me than this.
这是我可以想到的最好的解决办法
By the way, who taught you how to dance?
对了 你跳舞是谁教的
You did.
你教的
Well, I've done a fine job.
我教得还不错
Be careful.
小心点
(INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE)
(SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY)
Shall we go to work?
我们开始吧
Ladies and gentlemen, please, gather for the portrait.
女士们先生们 请集合拍照
I'm sorry.
不好意思
Is this a bad time?
没有打扰你吧
Never better.
来得正好
- Would you bring that clock?
- Heh.
能把钟拿来吗
We get to play that game after all.
终于有机会下棋了
Here we are.
披上这个
Don't want you to catch a cold.
我可不希望你感冒
A five-minute game?
下五分钟快棋
If you think you can manage it.
只要你没问题就行
(GUESTS CHATTERING)
We both have two bishops.
我们每人有两个象
I may be absent from the room,
but my methods are not.
我人虽然不在房间里 但我的战术还在
You can't mean Dr. Watson, surely.
你该不会指望华生大夫吧
That doesn't seem fair.
这样不太公平
Right. The surgery will have left scars.
好的
手术会留下伤疤
Only four of them have the hairline to hide them.
只有四个人的鬓脚能够藏得住
The ambassador that you replaced
with Rene, is he still alive?
被你用芮内掉包的大使 他还活着吗
Would you like me to recommend your next move?
要我提示你下一步棋怎么走吗
They're all my brother's height, right build...
都和我弟弟差不多高
体形也一样 但是
...but their eyes.
他们的眼睛
颜色不对 芮内是蓝眼睛
Their eyes are wrong. Rene has blue eyes.
He could be wearing glass lenses to change the color.
可能是带了能变色的玻璃镜片
In which case, his eyes will be hurting.
如果这样 眼睛应该会疼
Rene is left-handed.
芮内是左撇子
HOLMES: Perhaps the assassin will take measures...
也许杀手会采取措施来避免暴露身份
...Io ensure he doesn't give himself away.
Like a gambler concealing a tell.
就像赌徒掩饰手上的牌
(INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE)
I think it might be him.
我感觉 可能是他
You think?
你感觉
Your clock is ticking.
你的钟还在走
You have to be sure.
你可得肯定
MORIARTY: May I remind you, this is blitz chess
我提醒你 这可是快棋
A single miscalculation will cost you the game.
一次计算失误就会全盘皆输
If I tackle the wrong man to the
ground, I could start a war.
如果把其他人摁倒在地 我就引发战争了
HOLMES: Maybe it's less obvious.
也许没那么明显
A nervous tic. A ﬂutter of anxiety.
紧张的跺脚 一阵焦虑的躁动
I expect everyone has a reason to be nervous tonight.
我想今晚每个人都会有他紧张的理由
I don't know.
我不确定
(INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE)
HOLMES: So perhaps it's the opposite:
也有可能恰恰相反
A failure to behave naturally.
他没有了自然表现
An actor so consumed with his performance...
一个演员太专注于他的表演
...that the one characteristic
he cannot accommodate...
以至于他唯一不能表现出的
...is spontaneous reaction.
就是下意识反应
(PEOPLE GASPING)
(IN ROMANI)
我的弟弟
我求你了
(IN ROMANI)
姐姐 原谅我
(SHOUTS IN FRENCH)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
卡罗瑟 保护首相大人
Carruthers, protect the prime minister.
(RENE SCREAMING)
(IN ENGLISH) Germany will pay! Mark my words!
德国会付出代价的
That doesn't bode well, does it?
似乎不太顺利 对吗
Seems your bishop was of some benefit after all.
看来你的象多少有点作用
The game is still young.
胜负还不明朗
Actually, it's in its adolescence.
其实胜负已经有定数了
(RENE CONTINUES SCREAMING)
RENE: There are more of us!
我们还有很多人
Germany will pay!
德国必须付出代价
(RENE GRUNTS)
(WOMAN SHOUTING IN FRENCH)
(PEOPLE MURMURING)
No loose ends.
不留后患
(PEOPLE CHATTERING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
What happened to him? I'm a doctor. A doctor!
他怎么回事
我是个医生 是医生
(RENE GASPING)
(CHATTERING)
(GUARDS SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
SIM (IN ENGLISH): What happened?
出了什么事
- Curare.
- What's wrong with him?
是箭毒
他这是怎么了
It's poison.
他中毒了
Do something!
救救他
(SIM SPEAKS IN ROMANI)
Doctor, do something!
No.
(BOTH SPEAK IN ROMANI)
快来人啊 我的天哪 快救救他
(SHOUTS IN ROMANI)
(SIM SHOUTING IN DISTANCE)
I think you've just lost your most valuable piece.
我想你刚丢了最重要的棋子
But a winning strategy sometimes
necessitates sacrifice.
制胜的策略有时候需要做出牺牲
A war has been averted.
战争被避免了
Mm. Oh, I disagree.
我不这么认为
How so?
怎么说
Didn't you find it strange that the telegram you sent...
你不觉得奇怪吗 你所发出的电报
...didn't inspire any action to stop me?
居然没有给我带来任何的阻挠
You see, hidden within the unconscious...
听着 在潜意识的深处
...is an insatiable desire for conflict.
隐藏着对冲突的无限渴望
So you're not fighting me so much
as you are the human condition.
所以与其说你反对我
不如说是在反对人的天性
All I want to do is own the bullets and the bandages.
我想要的无非是拥有子弹和绷带
War on an industrial scale is inevitable.
工业时代的战争是不可避免的
They'll do it themselves within a few years.
不要几年他们自己就会打起来
All I have to do is wait.
我所要做的
就是等待
I like Switzerland.
我喜欢瑞士
They respect a man's privacy here.
他们尊重个人的隐私
Particularly if he has a fortune.
尤其是那些有钱人
Bishop takes knight. Check.
象吃马 将军
The game is over.
棋已经下完了
You should get that shoulder looked at.
去把肩伤治一下吧
About that fortune of yours.
关于你那些财富
I believe it's just been substantially reduced.
我恐怕它已经明显地缩水了
King to rook two.
王向车两格
I attended several of your lectures.
我听过几次你的讲座
这是运动公式 在我的书里也提到过
The equations of motion, which
you will find in my book.
The energy that is required to
release these explosions is...
释放这些爆炸所需要的能量就是
HOLMES: It was in Oslo when I first caught
a glimpse of your little notebook...
我是在奥斯陆第一次看到你的小手册的
...red leather-bound from Smythson of Bond Street.
邦德街斯迈森出品的红色皮面本
Rook to king's rook three. Check.
车向王车移动三格 将军
Bishop to rook three.
象向车三格
Its importance was not fully apparent to me...
我一开始不知道它的重要性
直到我观察了你喂鸽子的小爱好
...until I observed your penchant for feeding pigeons.
然后我想到
Then it occurred that with an empire so enormous...
经营如此庞大的产业
...even you must keep a record of it somewhere.
就算是你也要做一点记录
Bishop takes bishop.
象吃象
Rook to bishop four.
车向象四格
I then only required the notebook itself.
接下来就是要弄到这手册
You didn't make it easy.
这并不容易
(HOLMES SPEAKS IN FRENCH)
先生 您的外套 谢谢
Just the bags.
拿行李就行了
I would need to endure a considerable amount of pain.
为此我承受了相当的痛苦
(GASPS)
HOLMES: Mycroft...
迈克罗夫特
...care of Her Majesty's Secret Service.
女王陛下的密探
But the notebook would undoubtedly be encoded,
so how then to break the code?
但是这本子上的内容无疑是加密的
我该如何破解呢
- Rook takes rook.
- Pawn takes rook.
车吃车
兵吃车
Bishop to bishop seven.
象向象七格
后 吃掉马和兵
Queen takes knight pawn.
Does The Art of Domestic Horticulture
mean anything to you?
那本《室内园艺的艺术》
你还记得吗
How could a man as meticulous
as you own such a book...
为什么像你这么细心的人有了这本书
...yet completely neglect the flowers in
his own window box? Irony abounds.
但是窗台上的花却无人打理
这太荒谬了
Never mind, it's safe, in London...
别担心 它很安全
在伦敦
...where my colleagues are making good use of it.
而我的同事正对其善加利用
（《室内园艺的艺术》）
The most formidable criminal mind in Europe
has just had all his money stolen...
欧洲最不可一世的犯罪首脑的全部家产
...by perhaps the most inept inspector
in the history of Scotland Yard.
刚被伦敦警局史上
最没用的督察给抄走了
Any chance of a cup of tea?
能给我倒杯茶吗
Box 0403.
０４０３号箱子
CLARK: Tick. MARY: Box 0801.
有了
０８０１号箱子
- How much more is there?
- That's the end of page two.
还有多少
第二页结束了
Page three.
第三页
（当心你钓的鱼）
He'll be making an anonymous donation to
the Widows and Orphans of War Fund.
他会把钱匿名捐给
战争遗孀和孤儿基金会
Bishop to bishop eight. Discover check.
象向象八格 将军
And, incidentally, mate.
很不巧的 死棋
I seem to have injured my shoulder. Would you mind?
我的肩膀好像受伤了 帮我一把好吗
Be my pleasure.
非常乐意
Once we've concluded our business here...
等我们这里的事情办完之后
...it's important you know...
你知道我一定会
...I shall endeavor to find the most
creative of endings for the doctor.
找到最有创意的方式来了结那个医生
And his wife.
和他的妻子
HOLMES: His advantage, my injury.
他的优势是我有伤在身
My advantage, his rage.
我的优势是他急火攻心
Incoming assault feral, but experienced.
他的攻击很鲁莽 却也很犀利
Use his momentum to counter.
利用出拳间隙 予以反击
MORIARTY: Come now.
别傻了 你真以为只有你会玩这一套吗
You really think you're the only
one who can play this game.
抓住手臂 攻击他的弱点
Trap arm. Target weakness.
Follow with haymaker.
紧接着重拳挥击
HOLMES: Ah. There we find the
boxing champion of Cambridge.
真不愧是当年剑桥的拳击冠军
MORIARTY: Competent, but predictable.
反击有效 但容易看穿
Now allow me to reply.
现在轮到我来回应了
HOLMES: Arsenal running dry. Adjust strategy.
火力难以为继 要调整策略
(GROANS)
MORIARTY: Wound taking its loll.
伤势的影响开始体现
HOLMES: As I feared. Injury makes defense untenable.
如我担心的 肩伤让我无力防守
Prognosis increasingly negative.
预期结果 会越来越糟糕
MORIARTY: Let's not waste any
more of one another's lime.
让我们别再浪费彼此的时间了
We both know how this ends.
结果我们心里都清楚
HOLMES: Conclusion, inevitable.
推理完毕 必死无疑
(BOTH CHUCKLE)
Unless...
除非
(GRUNTING)
WATSON: A few words may suffice
to tell the little that remains.
故事的尾声无需赘述
Any attempt at finding the bodies
was absolutely hopeless.
任何寻找尸体的努力都以失败而告终
And so there...
因此在那
...deep down in that dreadful caldron of
swirling water and seething foam...
宏伟雄壮的漩涡和奔腾不息的浪花之下
将永远长眠着
...will lie for all lime...
（深情缅怀夏洛克-福尔摩斯）
（他下了一盘以大局为重的好棋）
...the most dangerous criminal...
一个最危险的罪犯
(INAUDIBLE DIALOGUE)
...and the foremost champion
of the law of their generation.
和那个时代最伟大的正义先锋
I shall' ever regard him as the best...
在我心中他永远都是
(TYPEWRITER KEYS CLACKING)
...and the wisest man whom I have ever known.
我见过的最优秀最智慧的人
MARY: John?
约翰
- John.
- Mm-hm.
约翰
嗯
You should probably pack.
你该收拾东西了
It's half past 2...
现在两点半 马车四点就来了
- ...and the carriage is coming at 4.
- Mm.
嗯
It's gonna be a beautiful week in Brighton.
我们会在布莱顿度过美妙的一周
Yes, it'll be fun.
一定很开心
I'm looking forward to it.
我真的非常期待
You know I miss him too..
我也非常想他
...In my own way.
用我的方式
（终）
He would have wanted us to go.
他肯定不希望我们成行
(CHUCKLES)
He would have wanted to come with us.
他一定想跟我们一起去
When's Mrs. Hudson coming for Gladstone?
哈德森夫人几点来接格莱斯顿
Oh, soon.
应该快了
Three o'clock.
三点钟
Mary?
玛丽
Who delivered this parcel?
这包裹是谁送来的
MARY: The postman.
邮递员
WATSON: The usual chap or...
以前那一个还是
...did he look peculiar?
看上去有点诡异
(WHIMPERS)
(SNORTS)
（终？）